okay um are we recording now yeah
alright so welcome to voices with Herve
key my guest today is Brad Cooper Brent
and I have had some email exchanges and
we've had already one extended zoom
conversation and I found Brent very
thought-provoking and I think his voice
should be heard more in this community
and so I'm hoping we can start something
together here today and get get his
voice into voices with verve a key and
into the community in general so welcome
Brent it's a pleasure to have you here
thank you likewise and hmm I think our
work has a lot of intersections and yeah
I'm excited to explore that right well
that's great so maybe you say a little
bit about yourself and how you know even
a bit of biographical history about how
you're vectoring into all of this
whatever this is part of what we're
gonna discuss is what all of this is I'm
just using big hand gestures right now
yeah so you can yeah like how do you
come into this and what you see your
role to be what would you like your role
to be etc sure I'll use a phrase that I
used with layman the other day because
it's uh it's actually from a book about
about think tanks but relegated
autonomous sociologists I'm a kind of
Perak academic and go against the grain
you know very very critical from the
radical tradition that studied political
sociology and international relations
and political sociology is about
actually the relationship between
knowledge and power and elites and
masses so that that's you know
international relations open my eyes and
then political sociology helped give me
laser vision to sort of focus in on you
know this these particular issues it's
really you know that took me to the cusp
of post-modernism and discourse and all
these things and paradigm shift and
where we're going so I've been on that
path for about 10 years and interest
didn't matter modernism and then
connected with meta moderna in 2016 and
and it's been a it's been a real treat
but also a lot of frustration to to be
to have a community to be involved with
and to see what that's like and
experience the different ideas and
frictions and hierarchies and you know
how we how we mitigate that and so a lot
of my critique is has taken me you know
in some ways back to post-modernism
necessarily and my side view article
actually goes into that yeah hmm but
yeah it's kind of kept me on the liminal
edge uh you know of critiquing those
that I admire and and care about and and
you know including people I work with
and including the intellectual dark web
which we'll talk about yes and and back
back to meta modernism you know what is
this project and where are we going and
how can we how can we I mean it's a
process so we're not gonna get there so
to speak but how can we recursively
iterate the process so that I mean maybe
this is a good segue that I mean I have
talked to layman Pascal that's the
layman he was referring to and and I've
talked to him about this question and in
christmukkah Pietro and I are writing an
article for apology that layman is
helping to supervise and I believe Brent
is also contributing to that as well and
we've also done some things as Brett
mentioned on the online journal the side
view but what this long preamble is to
say I have some sense and I have a book
that Brett recommended it's arrived they
haven't started reading it but since we
have Brent here what's what's your take
on this notion of meta modernism what
what what do you hear when you hear that
word what does it mean to you and what's
happening in it right now yeah what when
I first came across it
it was you know roughly the time I was
at grad school in London ten years ago
when vermeulen and van Acker were were
doing their work and I really had a
sense of it myself but I couldn't you
know I was so far from articulating it
it was just such a big big idea what I
was in going in going around in the
sociology department saying we need a
meta turn you know I was talking about
and there was also like like a
complexity kind of think tank at at the
London School of Economics and I think
it had been like shut down or defunded
or something and at the same time the
Arab Spring was happening and and and
and occupy and at the same time also in
within this year the director of LSE
kind of resigned in shame because he had
taken money from Gaddafi it's a lot to
let his son study there and so just
where I was at you know politically and
intellectually all these things
intersected and I did my dissertation on
the zeitgeist movement and so that you
know that that brought up this concept
of con spirituality which was also of
the time and kind of the the merging of
New Age and conspiracy and so you know I
saw this convergence and it and and you
know I was on the edge of you know
things like Joe Jack and Foucault and
and and discourse and you know just
again wondering wondering where it was
all gonna go and and how we could you
know translate it because a lot of the
the language you know postmodern
gibberish is the kind of expression
right so of academic language can be
very alienating so you want to you know
you ask the question like what is this
really about how can we get to the point
and so you know more language was just
nested within academic subfields and it
didn't really do anything right it was
impotent and so in some ways a lot of
this anticipates what happened you know
with with the intellectual dark web and
anti post-modernism hmm where where was
I going with
what was your question again oh yeah
yeah right yeah so so so just to kind of
fast forward you know I kept developing
my own ideas and from 2010 to 2015
you could google searching and you would
not find a lot about this term right
really very little so so there was no
discourse to sink your teeth into and
then I discovered a meta moderna right
this kind of thing tanked and they they
hadn't yet published their book but but
they were publishing articles and so I
thought that was fantastic you know I
think Hansie does a great job of
abstracting what this paradigm is and
there's some heuristic shortcuts taken
but I was ok with all of it you know I'm
on board the whole the whole modern post
modern meta modern thing it's not
entirely arbitrary but it's a little bit
slippery right there's other ways to
frame this you know because there's
other terms there's there these concepts
are nested the fractal
I think Hansie gets all this but he
simplifies it for the sake of this
system building right so so I got
involved with them so you know to a book
called The Listening Society right by
Hans e frying act and he's got two books
out now and it's you know part of a long
term vision and series and and I think
it's it's going well and so you know
they they took inspiration from what
Vermeil and and van de knacker were
writing about culture and so did I with
my film the abstract in terms of you
know metafiction and sincere irony and
all these things so so the discourse was
was working but it was still very
nascent right very very young and so you
know getting involved with that
community was interesting because
different people had different ideas or
lack of ideas and um Hansie kind of just
you know kept it kept it free and open
you know it wasn't like you have to
follow my theory but that is kind of the
implication as well which is a good
thing and you know so I I did two things
I tried to
the discourse and help develop a more
formal theory of what Madame modernism
is and my is my side view article is
kind of the latest installment or
culmination of that synthesis you know
thanks because I have a spreadsheet of
light 270 sources now and there's
there's more sources coming out of
course but it's hard to keep keep track
of but that was a you know aggregate the
discourse so everyone can see what's
being said everywhere you know I think
that's just an important research
function that you know other think tanks
or scholars were doing but then the
other thing was you know developing it
implicitly through my own work so you
know I've got I've got the film mm-hmm
and then all which is about abstraction
and then all my research about
abstraction and then the kind of like
adjacent research interests that I have
like evolutionary globalization and
systemic conspiracy which are kind of
two sides of the same coin and what each
of those do is kind of like looks at the
the latest wave of scholarship on those
topics and it's very synthetic and
syncretic tries to integrate them so I
try to develop a kind of meta modern
sociology implicitly through those and
there's some other fields I'm interested
in that I've that are less developed but
abstraction and meta modernism are also
- I've written about quite a bit
whether it's kind of a cultural
commentary or you know art commentary or
the the more the more high theory stuff
so lately that has really crystallized
into a convergence theory into my hopes
and intentions for consensus building
which I've been really on about for a
long time but finally wrote about and
then most recently anti-intellectualism
which which ties a lot of this stuff
together because there's as the this
think-tank book that I referenced and
has many other sources suggests there's
a kind of subtle anti-intellectualism
that takes place between us between
intellectuals and so you know we you
know just
we commit all sorts of fallacies even if
we're aware of them but perhaps one of
the ones that stuck out to me the most
is the Steve fuller this a scholar of
social epistemology describing mmm
heuristics as anti intellectual you know
the availability bias in particular is
anti intellectual and that really that
really struck me because that's along
the lines of you know my critiques of
integral people like Ken Wilber people
of course like Jordan Hall who talk in a
lot of these kind of neologisms or
simplicity's and things like the blue
church and read religion which I've
criticized for just being lifted from a
trump thread that these are you know so
when you think in those terms you're
collapsing into the availability bias
and and and you're using somebody else's
words to do your thinking for you and
and so Steve fuller identifies that as a
kind of anti intellectual bias and I
think getting into the subtlety of this
has been really interesting for me
because you know there's so much to
unpack about what the intellectual
tradition actually is what the radical
tradition is because you know we we we
tend to forget historically some of the
more important thinkers or political
actors right they get whitewashed and
and erased and you know there's there's
statues of all these Confederate it's a
you know heroes or whatever and and
they're being they're being torn down
that now and that's not to erase history
that's actually to remember history
properly right it's kind of historical
revisionism so so there was a lot in
there
Brent yeah pick up a couple threads so
one thread that I thought because I'm
still sort of one I want to probe you
more about their modernism brand right
you need to come up what seem to come up
as towards the end is something that I
work in which is I think why you
mentioned it I do work on you know
rationality and things like the
availability heuristic and the
relationship between heuristic and bias
and rationality and and then there was a
lot in your there also at least I think
directly implied that implicit
that sense about you know the importance
of dealing with self-deception whether
or not it's individual or collective
yeah those are things I talk a lot about
them something I'm very interested in so
one of the ways I've heard people talk
about these three categories and I grant
you they're there they're on a continuum
and they're slippery but we need to talk
we need to have some points of reference
for our discussion right one way I've
heard people talk about modernism
post-modernism and meta modernism and I
had a good discussion on leather wiki
with David Chapman about this is
especially in their conception of
rationality the conception of what
rationality is and that seemed to be
part of what laymen was saying when I
was asking so is that is that a fair way
of trying to get you know a doorway into
this but thinking about others agree
conceive of rationality now part of my
point I just if I can just make one more
point part part of my critique of what
has typically been called modernity and
what I think was implied in
post-modernism us especially in aspects
of some aspects of Derrida but we can
put that aside for now is that I'm
thinking of his his criticism of logos
centrism for example is that what
modernity had a very truncated and
strangulated notion of rationality and
post-modernism basically critiqued that
and then what I heard laymen saying to
me was well and this really saying to me
because this is part of my work right
there's no no we need we need to bring
back a more encompassing notion of
rationality in which ideas about
overcoming self-deception and more
recognition of bias in our thought plays
a much more fundamental role in sort of
formal logical consistency and so that
has been something that I've been I'm
offering that as a point of connection
so that I can better understand between
my work and and meta modernist is that
is that a useful thing to just to to try
and explore yeah I think so yeah I got
derailed there with my definition of
meta modernism by the defective part of
the story and I think you know the term
trans rational comes to mind right and
so there's maybe a kind of progression
from rational to post rational the trans
rational sure and and yeah and you know
we don't we never want to be
reductionist right that's the tendency
with thinking about these things and so
that's what I saw in people in the
integral community when they would try
to you know download meta modernism or
even integral you know and and again
with the heuristics to rely on the kind
of integral heuristics and this and the
stage theories so slow down yeah
interested in that too because again
this is something that I've only had
passing on connection with I'd never
spoken with Wilbur okay I've yet to read
any of his work in depth I bought his
book on the recommendation of notion
called the religion of tomorrow because
I'm trying to read books they're trying
to talk about the future of religion so
what can you can you can you slow that
down and unpack it a little bit because
maybe you know that will also help me
understand better you know what you mean
by translational your criticism of
integral like what is them what is the
what's here is it is it a kind of
oversimplification that you're putting
your finger on or what is it you want to
expand on that um yeah I I just wanted
to mention the term I don't I don't know
how deep I can go into it just off off
the top of my head because I want to I
just want to I want I want I want to get
an example where I can see you're
thinking like doing it's critical work
and that was something that I had
rationality and then I have like I said
I'm not invested in integral I'm trying
to understand it I know layman has a
history with it and he's had you know
I'm trying to get a sense there so I try
to find a point of contact for us yeah
and and I don't want to be too
reductionist stew with integral because
there's sort of non Wilbur forms there's
people have criticized Wilbur so a lot
of this has taken place within that
community before and that's part of for
me the the ironic frustration and
obscene a tree emerge in its kind of
crude forms because so I wrote about a
part article about the relationship
between integral meta modernism and the
intellectual dark web oh that's great we
can is that close enough in your memory
could up we could unpack that a bit yeah
yeah I can try because it emerged
basically you know because there's so
many integral people in Hans E's
community and they would say like
integral /mm like they're the meta
martyrs and like they're the kind of the
same thing and I was I had to do a lot
of work to kind of try to disentangle
that for people because I the same well
there's you know there's formula and and
and an actor and they don't mention
integral at all like it's a different
tradition right and so just people tend
to get hung up on that integral term
because there's a community there's a
lot of books they've invested so much
energy into it and and maybe just to tie
that off what we can we can go into it
but but the thing that comes to mind
first is in those articles I reference a
book from 2015 which is Eckstein is
involved in actually yeah called meta
theory for the 21st century right and
the whole point in that book there's a
table I take from the book it basically
tries to triangulate and synthesize
three major paradigms which is integral
theory critical realism and complex
thought and and the table kind of
juxtapose them so so that tells you
right there that you can't just have
integral theory these other things that
are well developed and and it's
interesting because the general critique
of integral the takeaway is that it was
kind of negligent of social justice
right it's like progressive and in name
but a little bit like conscious
capitalism instead and so that that kind
of divide in our thinking exists today
you know people lack the language to to
you know D complexify capitalism and
socialism
you know actually make these things
operational so the way the intellectual
darkweb fits into that is you know at
that point ken wilber had put out some
videos like that were kind of his
commentary on the on the IDW and it was
like me
yeah Wilbur had Wilbur had a like a six
part series you know and and so you know
at that point other integral people like
the names Mark Forman and Rob Smith come
to mind and I'm Corey DeVos to some
extent like they'd already been critical
of the IDW and there wasn't even that
kind of collective thinking that it had
like trickled up to Wilbur so I found
his position just really really weak
really diluted like oh yeah all these
thinkers are second tier like that's
just so irresponsible and a little bit
incoherent I think because this is a
kind of metaphorical system so so
there's all those intersections you know
and then like Eric Weinstein and tweeted
out like oh what Ken Wilber knows who I
am and that's interesting but you know
Weinstein wasn't necessarily like
endorsing integral or anything and you
know rebel wisdom like a big part of
their their branding for awhile I was
like who is the intellectual darkweb
integral like is Jordan Peterson
integral I did think it was totally the
wrong question you know okay
so in what wait so you you took time to
like to pull apart I mean it sounds like
it was a bit of a challenge pull apart
meta modernism from integral because
people were just treating them as
synonyms and you thought that was a kind
of deep conceptual mistake one of the
things that again I'm very hesitant like
I said I'm pronouncing and announcing
I'm ignorant of a integral I only know
of it I've read so secondary stuff so
please take that into account but and
I've met people who've talked about it
and I don't see the concern with
self-deception and rationality and maybe
that relates to your critique about not
addressing issues of social justice yeah
oh sorry if I if I can clarify that that
point quickly oh because I
what I wanted to add was like there's
there is sort of integral left tradition
if you will and also kind of activity
now right and you know exact size Equus
involved sure with that book and arguing
on the social justice side in debates
and so you know I sort of work with
Jeremy Johnson a little bit and he's
like a left activist an integral thinker
and he draws from a different from
different sources but I think there is
some compatibility just to a brief
overview of integral I guess it's like a
long term kind of you know synthetic
thinking right so you have like mystics
involved right and then you and um you
know like someone I promote a lot is
Michael Brooks who also has an integral
background right but he but he shares my
critiques and that he kind of grew out
of the Ken Wilber version of integral
and we so all of us now we try to bring
it back to politics and make it grounded
yes I just wanted to add that qualifier
well no - fair enough and I do want to
be fair I mean you'd probably know from
my work that I try to get as much credit
and recognition as possible the people's
work and you know I know Zac and I
really appreciate his work I just got a
book today by the way an education
between two worlds but there was
something that came up so see my
connection to integral is I know it
through transpersonal psychology and I
know right know forgave Ferrara's
critique of standard transpersonal
psychology as being tied to a perennial
astride of epistemology and therefore
not really philosophically or cognitive
scientifically up-to-date in terms of
its epistemology and its thoughts about
cognition and meaning-making and I want
to meet forever I never have
but he was one of the influences on my
idea participatory knowing because he
argues that a much more participatory
epistemology is needed than the one
that's presupposed by standard
especially Wilbur's form purely
structural kind of well seems fairly
structural kind
of transpersonal psychology so I get
that and and that's how the mystic is
supposed to be taken in but it seems to
me that one of the things that
post-modernism does is wake people up to
implicit epistemologies and get them to
stand back and take a more critical eye
on them and this is a kind of the deep
addressing of self-deception that you
and I think we'll share and so it seems
to me therefore that because is it fair
to say that one of the distinctions
between so it's a question what a
statement is it is it that one of the
distinction between meta modernism and
integral and the IDW is that meta
modernism takes post-modernism very
seriously and says that there's lots of
good work and good argumentation there
the IDW one of my critiques of it and I
think that's explicit is that I don't
think it has the reliance for example on
Hicks's presentation a birthmark
I think you know just it's just bad it's
just bad bad philosophy bad work right
and so I think the IDW did not take
post-modernism seriously yeah
intellectually it took it seriously in
terms of an emotional reaction to it but
not intellectually now it sounds to me
so this is more again very much more
hesitant but it's not to me like
integral also isn't properly reading or
understand being if if Ferreras critique
is good and it seems to be good that
suggests to me it implies to me that
integral did not take the postmodern
revelation of implicit epistemologies
and the critique of it that integral
hasn't also has not taken that seriously
enough in general at least that the the
vil the Wilber version would you what do
you think of that am I making oh yeah I
mean no no I mean that's that's
absolutely on point that's that's sort
of a point I'm
in my in my IDW critiques and it's out
and yeah especially if you're drawn to
meta modernism it seems very obvious
like how do people not realize this but
but for 30 years there's been a kind of
culture war over post-modernism right
like a lot of this is rehashed stuff
from the 90s because the you know you
know we don't it's a kind of systemic
thing we don't need to point fingers too
much but it's like the you know
post-modernism in the 90s was was waning
and declining and there was critiques
and and it you know it like first of all
it's irreducible right that's the point
I'm making my side view so so aside the
article so there's more than just
strengths there like it's a whole era
it's a whole you know multiple
discourses but but that that's that
fractionation and fragmenting you know
is part of the problem with our ever
expanding a culture right it's just a an
increasingly relativist right so so I
think people noticed and you know in the
2000s you have these other discourses
like post post-modernism right that's
actually a term which is funny it's like
well what is that the best you could
come up with why don't we just jump to
meta modernism right but I
another thing with my research is I'd
actually found sources on meta modernism
from the 90s that you know they're very
good sources but they're not huge
they're not like mmm they're very strong
arguments but they're not well developed
beyond that and so it's sort of a missed
opportunity and then there's all these
other discourses hyper modernism trans
Mormon ISM so I'm interested in all
these things but meta modernism has the
most generative potential and the
communities around them right so that is
that is really the the the main the main
attractor and so so I tried to map out
as much of that as I could in my
side-view article and but just to to
bring it home like your your point is
absolutely correct they just didn't they
the IDW dismisses and
post-modernism wholesale and integral
did go through a phase where they were
critical of it you know and Wilbur calls
it the mean green mean green mean and so
you know it was processed in a way but I
but it wasn't it wasn't it wasn't
healthy it wasn't conclusive because
there's just so much there and so you
know it's really a mental feat - to
whether implicitly or explicitly try to
try to be synthesizing the modern ideas
and postmodern ideas yeah and I think
you do it a bit in your in your side you
article like like your side view article
is an incredibly dense incredibly
incredibly wordy and to do in fact this
is some words I actually had to look up
which which I have no problem admitting
but it's a but it's also not that common
you know I like to know my words but but
but it's incredibly dense neck in that
capacity which is great because you're
you know uh just just a compression of
the argument that you're making right
and I there's some definitely cement
modern qualities like you're you're
you're you're doing a very syncretic
things right and yeah consolidating a
lot of ideas into these into these
concepts like and then you list them out
like new and hasta sysm pseudo religious
ideologies ersatz mythologies yeah so I
want to pick up on this then because I
think I this feels like it's really
getting legs what we're doing here first
of all I mean I agree with you and
you've mentioned it a couple of times
and I just want to pause and expand it
for people it's it's actually I mean you
know conversation has to take place at
different levels and that's fine and
that's there and that's part of how it
functions but you shouldn't treat
post-modernism as if it's a homogeneous
single thing like so I can't claim to
have read all of these thinkers I mean
there's I've I've read three I've read
Derrida deeply studied in Foucault not
as deeply but I'm working
and then warty right and and and and
even their backgrounds are very
different you know Dario is very
dependent on SACEUR in a way that
Foucault is not an R or D comes out of
you know pragmatism he's mostly
influenced you know by James and Peirce
and Dewey right
and so like trying to put that all
together as it's as a single thing I
recommend instead this strategy
mom I'm recommend that what we should do
because these people I mean it's a
mistake to say they should be immune
from criticism I dislike that also I
also dislike the deification of
post-modernism as if no I mean for
example I think Han in his book the
agony of eros has a powerful critique of
Foucault that people should read right
but what I'm saying is you should look
at individual arguments by individual
thinkers and respond to them with
individual counter arguments or counter
proposals rather than a pastiche and I
think that's a very danger maybe that's
what you're meaning from when you're
talking about sort of giving in to the
availability heuristic and an
oversimplification strategy so for
example I think very does not like I can
make this argument extensively and I
have made it elsewhere so I'm just
gesturing it and so not I'm not asking
for your agreement I'm just giving an
example right but I think Derrida's
notion of difference can be compared
very insightful II to this notion I've
been working at from cognitive science
of relevance realization and I think
there's a lot of deep similarities there
and even his take on it having kind of
Neoplatonic
religious significance his connections
with negative theology are there to read
right and so but that also gives me a
way of saying by because I can connect
it to Cox I I can bring aspects in to
differ ons
that perhaps Derrida is overlooking you
know the whole stuff about embodied
extended embedded cognition isn't well
developed in in Derrida and so I think
and this is something I've been trying
to promote a general if you take a
specific argument and then have a
specific bridging you know
counterproposal to it then you can
actually enter into
useful dialogue with the postmodernist
and so now sorry this is a long preamble
but I take that and and feel feel to
correct me but I think that is an
example of what I see the meta monitors
trying to do like I see them entering
okay they here's a postmodern thing
here's you know something I can link it
to and then put them into dialogue and
see if I can move beyond it but not in a
dismissive fashion but in a dialogical
fashion so you're nodding so maybe I am
saying something that resonates with you
yeah everything you said there makes
sense and there's there's a couple
things I wanted to anchor into what
should I go first with mmm I mean as you
said post-modernism
not homogeneous and when you engage the
text of all these thinkers and or
debates you know it becomes less clear
who is a postmodernist and who's not you
know this idea of a label of a
postmodernist is is a kind of
counterproductive to to some extent
however you'll always come back into
these kinds of expressions because
within different subfields there are
kind of trends like you know English
literature whatever right it's like
they're well defined and so you you
won't you don't know until you actually
dive into the literature and that that
speaks to something you you mentioned
that you know some authors you haven't
read right like this is true for all of
us and and it made me think of a kind of
generational gap too because I think I
think older scholars like have read more
right then people like me however you
know that would for younger people you
know you have the internet now and we
have access to more sources than ever
and there's more coming out than ever
every day so there's no way you can keep
up with it you know and it's like you
have to kind of find a way to grok it
without reading it however that you know
to qualify that statement you do have to
read you do have to read as much as you
can you know so there's a real paradox
there and so I mean I realized this a
long time ago
that I was never going to catch up but
no
never gonna go for a PhD because PhDs
are about specializing actually I
consciously decided I was gonna be a
generalist which is a very difficult
path and it's very rare not a lot of
people do it and some people try to do
both right but you know so part of that
is you know I wanted to pick up on this
idea just because what you said
triggered a one thing don't you sure
don't lose your shirt but I just wanted
to point out something that Brent said
that I want to highlight and how it's
brought it's bringing out kind of a new
bias a new form of self-deception which
is and sloman talks about this in the
knowledge illusion people regularly
and reliably confuse access the
knowledge with the possession of
knowledge so a standard example of this
experimental II is do you do you know
how a bicycle works oh yes of course I
do well here draw diagram and show me
how a bicycle works and then people
can't do it now why did I bring that up
to give the point that Brent just made
about you know access to the Internet
actually magnifies that bias
tremendously people think because they
have access to all this information
that's the same thing as it being in
possession of I just wanted I just sorry
for interrupting but but I thought it
was an important point to fight for
people that you know we think about this
oh this access is so empowering
well no denying that but you also have
to understand ways in which it's
triggering and amplifying powerful forms
of self-deception so I just wanted to
put that in there bruh yeah thanks
that's that's helpful and and I think
that's you know that's true for me to
some extent too because I do get like
overconfident with with my knowledge
however the the flip side of that is
like like I'm constantly collecting and
downloading more books articles that I
can read right but but I'm but I'm
keeping conscious of the library that
I'm building you know and and it makes
me aware of what I would I might know
and what I definitely don't know so it
keeps me humble at the same time right
good and yeah that's very good I I think
that's a that's a virtue towards which I
aspire yeah I try to do it by some very
explicit and repeated
repeated habits of action because I
think it's very important yeah so to
finish the point I was making before
like you know as a student you know when
we're students we're you know we're
we're all taught to read primary sources
right like like I need Plato like like
you know do you read and you know do the
work and because that is what you have
to do as a student it's an exercise it's
right so I remember back to a class in
2008 right and there and it is like a
third-year level class in in in
political theory and they're they're
just all they can do because they're
teaching students is kind of give you
the tools and teach you how to work with
them right and contrary to public
opinion with what the IDW tells you they
don't just indoctrinate you know at
least where I went to school they teach
you how to think very critically mm-hmm
but but you know they would teach you
theories and about international
relations like oh here's idealism here's
realism here's Marxism here's the
thinkers and then they actually tell you
like oh like they use the phrases like
the idealist would say well the realist
would say you know and that's useful as
a student but then of course that's a
kind of a gross simplification of how
these things work and so you don't want
to ratify those theories too much and
the point I wanted to make before is
like you know by all means like read
read Plato read read Nietzsche whoever
read jiseok whatever you want but this
idea of primary sources like primary
sources are essential but also they can
be wrong and so a kind of meta modern
move and maybe postmodern a bit too is
like you you you you want to value
secondary sources - so like with apart
take Marx for example right Marx is
prolific I've read some I've read a lot
more marks than Peterson has but I also
really trust certain secondary sources
right when you're reading scholars
writing about Marx you have to you know
this is I guess a postmodern thing first
and foremost but you have to think about
like well who are they what era and what
place are they writing in oh no how does
this situate in the lineage in the
well kind of evolution of Marxist
thought right and so it really defies
simplification and so so going back to
that point about you know not being able
to read everything and keep up with it
all this is and this is where it gets
meta modern right and I talked about
this idea of Auto critique in in my
anti-intellectualism article which is
like a self critique in like a hyper
critique of society the society that
you're in you know what are we doing
with war and imperialism very meta
questions and so I apply that to my own
work like because nobody's gonna be is
as critical as me you know I don't have
a dissertation advisor anymore well you
know I don't have an editor so with that
oh yeah I mean I think sorry for
interrupting but I think that's I want
to flag this I mean this is what I this
is what I think is at the core of this
meta modern notion of rationality is
like when when one of my students asked
me for like what's up what's the
criteria not a definition but what's a
criterion but you know we're gonna pick
up people that are more rational I say
look for people who are committed to
self correction look for people who are
committed to self direction rather than
uh you know just a formal tightness in a
monologue and so I've sort of augmented
to people who are interested in self
correction and are interested in
genuine good faith dialogue and trying
to specify what that means is I've been
doing a lot of work on that but I just
want to apply that because I think
that's another point that I think really
sings for me the fact that I heard you a
couple times in this discourse point two
areas in which you have been and
continue to be self-corrective I try to
do the same thing and so you know I'm
not claiming any expertise and that or
anything like that I'm just marking that
out as exemplification of how this other
kind of rationality is more properly
enacted I just wanted to say that yeah I
think more important to flag it that's
great and I like you pausing and you
know reiterating what's going on here
it's helpful and so to if I can quickly
tie back to like meta modernism and what
I've tracked with the different schools
of thought you know I like what Hansie
is doing I like what Thomas Bjorkman is
doing oh yeah
yeah yeah you know it's been it's been
uh it's taken me a while to get up the
nerve to talk about these things but but
I I like hearing other people talk about
it when they know what they're talking
about and I and you know because I'm
because I'm immersed in it so so that's
been really helpful but what they're
trying to do and I'm part of that
project right is they're they're
systematizing and they're they're
simplifying this kind of paradigm shift
and then so so in my side-view article
identify you know the kind of way that's
cool the gun school yeah they murdered
first yeah and just to clarify for
everybody I only call it the Dutch
school as a joke because primary authors
are from the Netherlands and they you
know they worked in London they work
with an international community of
scholars and it's and it's just a joke
and as I say in my review of their book
which is a great book I say their their
theory fits the social sciences like a
pair of clogs which is to say like kind
of awkwardly and you know wouldn't but
it's got a ton of potential right and so
so when you read Vermeulen and Bandar
knackers book they're referencing you
know Frederick James and Raymond
Williams and those are really important
sources for the background of all this
stuff right and I and going back to what
we're saying about about reading like
I've I've skimmed those books you know
I've got a gestalt
impression and I've read you know this
is the thing with second with secondary
sources so I trust them I trust their
reading but it's a kind of tentative
trust yeah because I'm also critical of
Rimula and Van Dekker for what I
identify is what they miss right so you
know a lot of my work wouldn't be
possible without them but I'm trying to
I'm trying to recursively and auto
critically feedback into that system and
so so that's sort of where are the the
contemporary use is popularized in kind
of you know describing trends in art and
culture and and then and then Hansie
makes a makes a formal move and does
exactly the same thing I'm advocating is
saying well we need a medic
turn in sociology and politics and and
and they do that see part of the second
because you said there's two groups for
Mehta modernism where's he still I'm
just trying to keep the taxonomy clear
yeah so the easy part of a Dutch group
or is he part of the other group the
other so I'm saying
Hansie and Hansie is what I call the
Nordic school ah right because they're
based in in Scandinavia but the the
fictional author Hans he's actually
based in Switzerland but but the Swiss
school just didn't sound right because
yeah I'm trying to talk about reality
here too so Thomas Bjorkman wants to
kind of separate himself from that but
they're they're they're kind of in the
same sphere but I'm in my article I make
a distinction I say the Nordic school is
just Hansie because they're actually
formalizing it and trying to build a
community and it's just a very I think
coach cogent and powerful system and so
you know that doing that it allows me to
distance myself from it and have a meta
perspective of the two schools and the
interplay and as I said to you at the
beginning like I've been developing my
alternative view the whole time but it
comes into clearer focus as time goes on
so let's let's just say that's the
abstract school because I I point to
thinkers like Benjamin Bratton who
invoke a ton of abstraction in their
work explicitly and I and I track
abstraction everywhere it goes right so
Daniel smocked and Berger uses it a lot
Jordan Peterson uses it a lot and
there's some there's some real value
there you know my first article about
Peterson was was sort of positive in
this regard but that of course I have
way more criticism for him than
compliments but so you know this all
this alternative is like I'm actually
trying to highlight some of the things
the other schools and put in the
background right so I have a missing
meta modernism series which highlights a
novel philosophy of technology
liberation theology mmm-hmm and and
black black mana modernism right so
that's actual focus on the the subaltern
the global South alter-globalization
Black Studies and of course I think
that's all very relevant more than ever
with all that's happening in the world
so I just want two questions keep in
mind what you're saying that so one is
just a because I'm ignorant so I'm just
doing it's a factual question in your
opinion like your studied opinion like
do these two do these because I didn't
get a clear sense in the article what's
the relationship between them is it
friendly is it biological or are they
sort of isolated from each other do they
talk a lot and then secondly so if you
could answer that question first like
this this notion about abstraction I
mean it's in the name of your think-tank
and that wonderful that that video
you've done that wonderful video on it
and that that sort of you know playful
irony you know really abstraction is
that the key yeah
and so maybe and maybe by answering the
first it'll give you a platform for
expanding on what you mean by this
process so first of all I'm like what's
is the relationship between the two
groups and then story for the pun but
maybe you want it what did you abstract
from that into your notion of
abstraction yeah I think I think there's
sort of a sort of a healthy separation
in in some ways but also unhealthy like
like they don't really talk that much
some of some of them talk like there's
some been some crossover with Greg
Denver for example he was in the side
view article and and for for a couple
years like we would just talk past each
other you know and I actually had to
invoke him a medic mediator to say there
is Jason Schneider I said you know bring
us together so we can figure this out
and so you know so what I call the Deaf
school doesn't even recognize honty you
know and which is it which is which is
unfortunate and interesting at the same
time because I think academically the
Hansie books are are quite formidable
you know it shouldn't be written off you
know Daniel is a PhD in sociology so I
have advocated for us to to talk but
it's never really half
so the the two schools kind of remain
distinct and of course the the original
ol school doesn't really see itself as a
school of thought they're just they're
just they're just academics but I have
identified lots of contrasts like I say
the former is more academic the latter
is more para academic you know and
there's there's a reason for that
there's a you know and it's interesting
so it gives meta modernism this this
aliveness this tension right and you
know that and and and so you know in
lieu of talking Hansie just makes a move
you know I think he says in the book
they kind of pirate the term from
Vermeulen and band records in a footnote
it's almost just in passing and and so
so there's that and and also you know
I'm trying to do something different if
I can by you know trying to have a
syncretic approach and look at the mall
and you and and and particularly you
know convert converge because I think
there should be a kind of unified body
of work you know not to say it's
homogenous it never will be but but um
you know so one of one of the things I
love mint in my side-view article too is
like year after year more articles will
come out on post-modernism you know and
it'll just be some hot take or new
insight or whatever but it's like you
know I'm bewildered how people can write
about this and just completely ignore
other things going on you know so like
like like the the book I recommend to
people for post-modernism is the
postmodern turn in the social sciences
and that came out in 2015 and in 2015
like you have you know years of kind of
production of all these alternatives
like meta modernism digi modernism trans
modernism hyper modernism but there's no
mention of any of those in the book and
and the book is very you know
encyclopedic and yet it still still
misses these things and then it's my
epic innocence then in a sense it's also
fractal I mean it's incredible I'm a can
own in my article like there's 1600
footnotes in the book like no books do
that like it's
all these endorsements from from big
sociologists so you know it it's just
it's it's very intimidating right in
that sense but but it gives you there's
all within it there's a lot of
simplifications like well here's the
five major turns in different fields
that this you know this is what
post-modernism is so um I mean right
there just to highlight that point you
know post-modernism Italy is at least
five things okay and and of course it's
much more than that but this is the the
mistake the IDW makes is just collapsing
it into one thing like oh it's
relativism
well relativism predates all yeah but
even if you read like weed Foucault like
I'll talk to people well it's funny to
broaden the critique oh this will happen
with it with people who through you know
speak those words and I'll say but have
you read the later Foucault you know
were the care of the south and he starts
reading Pierhead oh and he gets deeply
interested in ancient philosophy and the
wisdom tradition and that's and he saw
that as and I think rightly by the way
he saw that is the culmination of what
he'd been working on and I said there
you go yeah yeah and and and and and
Foucault you know mmm died before his
time yeah and that that could be true
for a lot of thing because I mean how
many thinkers have died without
finishing their their magnum opus right
they all have unfinished manuscripts and
it's it's so tragic and so that that is
part of a big part of what meta Mara's
meta morgan ism is for me is is really
trying to pick up their threads and
finish their project you know because I
remember in grad school ten years ago is
the kind of running joke that everybody
was trying to publish their manifesto
yeah and and and and actually you know
in 2011 Luke Turner published his meta
modern manifesto which was just eight
points right is really short and that
was a kind of tongue-in-cheek joke that
like on a number of levels but you know
in lieu of writing a big book it's like
this is this is it just eight points
about you know oscillation and irony and
whatnot so you know III accepted that
myself and I thought you know I I want
to write some books of course but not
too many books the the the thrust of my
project is to is to try to you know
participate in this long-term historical
process of knowledge creation and and
praxis right because to you know to tie
it to this idea of the meta-crisis you
know it's like it's this deep thing that
you only get a salience of when you've
really developed a complex perspective
and you've taken in a lot and you you
channel your concern for whatever social
issues that might be to singular or even
superficial like veganism and and I'm a
vegan I advocate it you know or or
whatever it's like or poverty it's like
okay that's one thing and the
meta-crisis is all these things are
connected yes and we reproduce it in
almost everything we do right so that's
the tragic irony of humanity is just how
how uh how how smart we can be and how
likes like transcendently stupid we can
be and and just disconnected from each
others worlds and projects and the
internet brings all that back together
right this globalization process which
has been happening for millennia is
actually converging into a climax and so
it's what we're trying to figure out so
before you get into that because I can
tell you that Villa mental I didn't want
to lose the thread because I think
you're also germinating an answer to my
second question was sort of your take on
like what you have like your notion of
abstraction and what you're taking from
this because it sounds to me like you're
you're for grounding the meta crisis and
and it's it's dynamical complexity as
something that you think meta modernism
should be addressing centrally is that
is that fair yeah that's that's that's
bang on and actually I have to mention
because it pops into my head this is not
an availability bias thing kind of is
but in 2015 there's no
article titled the meta-crisis of
secular capitalism and so you know
that's not typically what we're talking
about when we talk about this term but I
like it and that article in particular
highlights abstraction as part of the
key right financial abstraction so
capitalism abstracts and that that that
is a whole other conversation to unpack
or but let me just start over this term
for open up this term as you want as you
intend to use it
abstraction yeah please so um so I'll
try to just say something about that
article because it's basically about you
know the the the falling rate of profit
and and and there's some implicitness
about you know just the you know can
have infinite growth kind of thing so
capitalism is in crisis right but but so
to bring it back to the beginning so in
in all my studies you know and i think
we all have this to some extent
abstraction has come up in near work but
i would i would come across this term
you know and you read about like the
absolute you know in philosophy and
abductive logic you know abduction and
actually you you say in your article
that you're using inference to the best
explanation yes that is abduction that
is a deductive logic that's what it's
called and and so this is actually not
like this is actually like if I'm if
correct me if I'm wrong but it's not
such a common approach you know or
subtle than induction and deduction
right those are the marriages people
take yeah Brett my reason for not using
the term abduction is just as people
always misunderstand what it means and
and I was very influenced by especially
by Lipton and others who are recap and
so there's a little bit of a cottage
industry around this inference to the
best explanation yeah I found to be the
best interpretation of Darwin and etc so
yes and the reason why that comes up and
this is how maybe I somewhat like you
and being a generalist because cognitive
science you you know you know you know
specializing with one of the home
disciplines you have to read deeply and
study deeply and all of them but you're
trying to get us in
ethic integration which requires this
kind of adaptive reasoning is that part
of what you're pointing towards that
sort of abductive reasoning when you're
talking about down yeah for sure
oh that's absolutely fascinating to me
because I think it's the hallmark of
science I think it doesn't work in terms
of sorry I'll stop in a second I think
it doesn't work in terms of certainty I
think it works in terms of a different
normative 'ti plausibility which I've
been trying to get clearer about and the
thing about it is for me as a cognitive
scientist that's the form of reasoning
that really and this is a point I owe to
Jerry Fodor is really dependent on that
whole process that I talked about is
relevance realization which already is
really really key so I just want to say
if that's what you're talking about yeah
yeah there's just a lot that I can it's
not IntelliJ I can get into it I need it
what you're saying go ahead that's great
and that's exactly why I mentioned your
article and and you know I've alluded to
your other work on abstraction because
you know there's a good chance like well
I'm certain that in in some of this
regard you're you'll you're more of a
specialist of abstraction than I am
right and so is Benjamin Bratton right
and that this is why I defer to them but
it's just so fir to wind it back for the
sake of kind of telling the story what
happened to me 10 years ago was you know
abstraction kept coming up and also it
means different things in like abstract
art and you know I always it's as
interesting I always thought abstract
art was stupid and like like why is this
picture of a square worth so much money
and and and stimulating so much thought
and debate in people detail is making me
angry but then you know I I developed a
sort of deep appreciation for it and
just abstraction in general and so the
term comes up in all these different
sources in in in in cores if ski you
know and systems-thinking in marks right
and Hegel and and you know Nietzsche I
mean it's it's everywhere and it's
nowhere at the same time because
i-i-i i started to just develop a
practice of aggregating these sources i
have hundreds and hundreds of sources
and like with meta modernism it took me
a while to kind of get the ball rolling
there because i just found it really
elusive really hard to track and and and
and you know i bring up that meta-crisis
of secular capitalism article because
it's got abstraction right in the thesis
and also a book by Serna check and
Williams called inventing the future
right by verso press the leftist press
and and they have a lot of abstraction
in that book and it's like I would find
it in all these places and find it
talked about really cogently and and
really brilliantly these these people
know their work but there was no meta
theory behind it there was nothing tying
all the abstraction together and this is
perhaps you know an impossible project
but at minimum I'm trying to you know
chronicle and catalogue all the sources
because I just keep finding more and so
you know this is I've written like you
know you know 1314 articles on some
abstract some aspect of abstraction
right financial abstraction meditative
abstraction and art and all these things
and so this is why with my project like
it became artistic thing became a became
a film and it became a research project
a think-tank and and so you know I'm
still this is still in motion I still
have to you know read a lot more and
process a lot more but but I know in
aggregating that stuff like it kind of
puts me ahead of the curve in some ways
just because it's such a monumental task
you know I'm trying to like you know and
you know G that comes to mind because
he's me you know every time someone
mentions abstract in their speech it you
know I log it in my memory and I you
know think about what they're trying to
say what it means in the big picture and
she's actually in over fifty bucks
right he's prolific and so of course you
know Peterson didn't even bother
cracking one to prepare for the debate
this is too much and you
I've read a bit of jiseok and seen him
talk a bunch of times but you know it
also just goes on and on and so people
get kind of tired of them and people
have their critiques of jiseok so but
the steam of abstraction you know it's
it's the it's the fact that it's so
subtle and then it gets buried in our
research that is part of the
reproduction of the meta-crisis and so
there's a book from 1973 called the
abstract society and that was really
formative free because it's it's not a
huge book but it's very dense and its
thesis is basically you know society is
getting more abstract and he identifies
these these trends like you know
bureaucratize ation of course
specialization these are now like sub
functions of abstraction and they all
they all add up and you know we just
have this increasingly complex world and
so to to bring it back before I forget
with capital right so because Marx
talked about commodity abstraction right
and and and what what they call real
abstraction and there's a bunch of the
kind of speculative realists that that
write about this too like rain brassy
and like this is like it's the super
dense writing very hard to penetrate the
only one of those guys that I've read in
depth is Harman so I'd I say all right
ok only connection I have with it yeah
I've got a sense of it but that's I've
read a little bit of Morton yeah yeah
yeah so so to crystallize it basically a
lot of these authors throughout history
in particular some of these guys they
say there's not just mental abstraction
right because that's because you
especially as a cognitive psychologist
that might be what you what preoccupies
a lot of your interest
yeah but they say there's not just
mental abstractions there's like
abstraction in the world like material
abstraction and and it's this is super
interesting and really difficult what
does that mean
what does that mean yeah I was trying to
like set up is how difficult it is to
explain it means you know we we abstract
the world in the world abstracts us you
know this is just a process we're locked
into it's like the idea of like thinking
you know ideas think you or
ideas work through you rather than you
think ideas so can I just nail down the
reference of the world you're not you
mean yeah we're sort of like the
socio-cultural world it is is abstract
or do you actually mean the material
world so so I'll get to this so I'm
identifying a lot of these authors say
that there's two major forms which is
the thinking and the kind of material
that they call real abstraction and I'll
unpack that but just quickly you know I
did an article called integral
abstraction where I put it in the four
quadrants right so this is actually
really useful because because I'm taking
what most authors are saying oh there's
just two there's actually four so so I
say there's mental abstraction mMmmm
fuck it mental abstraction physical
abstraction social abstraction and that
material abstraction mental material and
physical yeah so some material would be
the upper right quadrant which is like
the the individual as opposed to the
collective so material is that on the
collective level okay
and so so oh yeah I mean I'm gonna try
to just keep it in the in the in the
binary frame cuz it's just plain but but
but just a social abstraction which is
not part of the binary that's that's the
lower left
that's the ideas that we share right so
the idea of a nation is a social
abstraction and so there's all these
quadrants are connected there's an
individual component to it all the
George Herbert Mead kind of idea right
that kind of abstraction I get that okay
okay yeah and and and so there's no
integration between these fields in the
different scholar scholarly traditions I
mean there might be implicitly there
might be a little bit explicitly but but
what I was reading is most of them just
for simple yet complex sake they say
that there's mental abstraction and
material and so Marx talks
commodity abstraction and the point with
that is that is that the abstraction
becomes like reified right it becomes it
just it becomes its own acting agent
that then that then you know creates the
world that we live in and so there's
there's a diet a dialectic process there
and and Bratton takes it way deeper he
he talks about primordial abstraction he
goes and so does Peterson they go way
back in time to when we were just you
know simple organisms and and the so so
animals abstract right but only in the
capacity of like sensing mapping you
know for for food Friend or Foe so it's
very primitive type of abstraction and
then what what Peterson says is you know
we kind of evolved and we go up and we
that that map's higher and higher to
philosophy ultimately like in play it's
a theory he gets that's Romero Sloane I
mean that's the idea right yeah pretty
much
idea yeah yeah so so again just to kind
of you know hedge my bets here the
material abstraction is really difficult
to talk about the you know the commodity
form and yeah I'm trying to get it is it
is it
well I offer this as a possible bridging
analogy because I'm trying to get it you
don't get it I'm trying to get it so
Aristotle talks about what I would call
like a metaphysical kind of abstraction
in that you have inanimate matter and it
gets informed and it becomes animate
matter and that's more abstract than
right and till trying to fix up on this
and then animate right it gets it
informed at another level of recursion
and it becomes you know psychological
and then ultimately rational and
rational is this is a it's an act is an
abstract form of being that can can self
abstract and self realized and so that's
a metaphysical abstraction it's not
taking place in the on buddy of mine
it's the yeah in the ontological
structure of beer yeah getting closer to
what you're you're talking about or is
it yeah I think I think maybe that's
maybe that's a better kind of heuristic
even because you have a whole scale
there but what I'm talking about it is
slightly different I mean it's all it's
all connected but let me try to bring it
back to Joe's talking about commodities
but then that that that abstracts into a
higher form of money right and so with
finance financial abstraction right we
you know you just have more and more
complex forms of money and finance and
that that is distance from the material
world right so there's so much distance
and so I don't know if you know about
modern monetary theory but that's the
kind of catchphrase that is becoming
more and more popular and and I it's
something I wrote about for for Thomas
Bjorkman that'll that'll come out soon
but it's a day-by-day there's more
coming out on it it's basically the the
theory that you know States and the
Federal Reserve you know have the kind
of prerogative to just print money right
just add numbers to the ledger
and that is possible because of how
advanced capitalism has become in terms
of abstraction yeah in terms of
abstraction exactly and it's become so
advanced that we can't keep up with it
and we don't even know what we're doing
and so so modern monetary theory is
already employed when there's a stimulus
package and it goes to you know
corporations and and whatnot and so that
that is very capitalist because you
actually want that money to go into the
hands of people right and so the debate
about modern monetary theory is is how
we add numbers to the ledger and what we
spend it on right and so bringing it
back to politics and what will keep it
on abstraction but just to finish this
money point you know we need to make
money more available to people and you
need to spend it on on development
social infrastructure not not bombs that
just blow up that money you know and so
this is what capitalism does though
through its functions of abstraction and
and particularly the advanced forms of
finance and now cryptocurrencies and so
we need to reverse that trend in some
ways and we also put like get out in
front of it and and you know it's like
stop a whole grade so and I mean I'm not
meaning this question facetiously I mean
it's seriously given what you just said
a moment ago
about the fact that the complexification
is dynamical right it's the
complexification it the complexification
is complexified but it's it's going up
an anomaly in your fashion I mean how do
and I mean this question seriously how
do we get out in front of that it sounds
like it's it's got a runaway you know
yeah I've got the answer that's good
it's not it's not easy but it's the way
you phrase the question sets me up
because that's that's great to take it
back to you know what do we do about it
in the mental abstraction so part of my
work is trying to unpack the mistakes
and the fallacies we're making in our
own mental abstraction yeah you know and
so you know we need a mass education
universal education so that the average
person has better mental abstraction
faculties to get whole world is this
where your work sort of intersects with
Zach's work ever than that yeah and
yours right because you want people to
have better relevance realization and
all these things right you know I'm
always bringing it back to the system
because it's not enough to like build
out these these capacities in small
groups right you need to actually
advocate for universal education right
yeah this is why I'm so passionate about
Bernie Sanders because he had a pretty
broad platform that included you know
green New Deal jobs guarantee and you
know debt forgiveness and and and and
free college you know this stuff is
really really important it has
consequences and so so to frame it in
terms of how we ideologically abstract
and I'm how we debated not even debated
we just argued over the past four years
about about you know who wore it well or
whatever you know we have the dumbest
conversations about politics and it's
and it's a function of bad abstraction
actually what I caught what's called
vicious abstraction so you know William
James talked about vicious abstraction
yes yes I'm James was an influence on
you because yeah what you're saying a
lot mm-hmm
yeah and so that particular concept has
a kind of twofold implications here one
is just the the general bad abstraction
out there like I've used can use Jordan
Peters's Peterson
as an example because look at how he
abstracts the concept of things like
Marxism or feminism right he viciously
literally viciously aggressively and
kind of violently collapses it into
singular meaning like Oh Marxism equals
communism actually you can't get more
anti intellectual than that on that
topic because that's like McCarthyism
and it's just it's for closing thought
and discussion right and so that's a
vicious abstraction but the context in
which I use this concept is actually an
article about systemic racism because
because it's interesting you know
there's a there's a Republican
strategist named Lee Atwater in the
active in the 60s and 70s and and he
uses the words abstract he's like you
know we we used to use these slurs but
you can't do that anymore so what we
done is we abstracted the you know the
politics and so you know this is part of
this dumbing down of culture and anti
intellectualism and you know now you
know the education secretary is Betsy
DeVos and she's extremely anti
intellectual you can hear he just
anti-education anti-alien air she's for
these things called what is it the the
vouchers vote you know schools charter
schools yeah mmm-hmm right and it's like
like there's so much going on there
mmm-hmm and what we need is more
universal access to quality education
right and you know big let lamentation
for a lot of us is like they don't even
teach critical thinking in high school
you know like this is basic but but part
of the critique of education is you know
just making people informed enough to
work and to be a compliant kind of kind
of populist and we're seeing that all
breakdown right the meaning crisis the
actual functional meta-crisis it's all
breaking down it is we we can't afford
such core weak vicious abstraction in
our thinking sure isn't there also I
mean I got to Thomas about this based on
his work the world we create because I
thought
his argument was there's also been and
it's both an abstraction and a reduction
and those don't have to be
contradictions to each other of our
normativity because he and I gotta do a
discussion about how all we we should
have multiple sources of normativity
this is kind of a harbor must point to
but you know his point is they've all
been defeated and we now have the de
facto you know one normativity of the
market and then and this this this
strikes me as convergent with Zack is
that can I've talked about this about
you know how the market the market
normativity has become the sole basis by
which we're evaluating educational
success and and I hope you'd be terrible
to me I'm not saying that economic we
should there shouldn't be economic
criteria in education and of course
there should be because it's positive
human being but we use that I mean if
you look you know classically look at
Plato's it B Academy right the
normativity there is not the market the
normativity there is virtue or you know
you know of course there's critiques of
the Platonic vision I'm just pointing
out that there have been long-standing
you know all through the Middle Ages
it's it's a religious normativity rather
than a market Nerva tivity driving
education university was originally to
make a person universal the liberal arts
the liberal a turn right high ideals
there yes well my ideals but they
weren't they weren't they weren't ivory
tower ideals they actually constituted
and regulated the educational project
and then we have basically put that all
aside for this other normativity which
got which seems to be I take this to be
as a critique it seems to be and maybe
yours it seems to be failing us in our
ability to produce well if you'll allow
me a really low determiner but I'm using
it you know resonating with the
classical traditions that I've invoked
here you know making good persons we
that used to be the project the project
right and we probably and then we tried
I think it already a diminished version
but we tried making good citizens and
then and then we've diminished that to
making good consumers
which which which I mean and that is not
nothing to a tremendous a lot of
difficulties like so when I see my kids
and and their cohorts the the lack of
depth and resiliency in their cognition
that that their education has afforded
them which i think is part of what
you're pointing to too
I think we have done them a great
disservice I think we have great
disservice because like I see the way a
lot of them are responding to the co vid
crisis and the way that's exacerbating
the meeting crisis getting it on
steroids in math yeah and and they and
they just don't have you know the the
the the you know the self complex
applying resiliency and sophistication
of cognition to to deal with this and
and that's not a criticism of them as
people that's not making criticism of an
educational system that has largely
failed to prepare them for reality so
that was a bit of a rant that's great to
say that yeah and it's so something I
continuously try to highlight is that
it's cut down in the most subtle ways
and that's how it that's how it happens
right under our noses
right so the liberalism in the 70s
emerging not by accident right but but
emerging you know what it was so you
know
so when laws and stuff are passed like
and the patriarchy Patriot Act was
passed without even being read you know
so there's so much abstraction in these
documents and people who are just like I
don't have time to deal with it right so
it's like how do you think neoliberalism
happens right it's like there's some
great ideas in theory and principle but
but they're there you know there's
vicious abstraction there and and before
I forget I thought maybe you want to
define that for people because we kind
of just rushed over it well I mean part
of what I understand James to mean is
and in Whitehead and Whitehead at a
similar one which is really interesting
is in many ways are so different the
fallacy of misplaced concreteness this
idea that we can mistake our abstraction
and we can we can attribute them to a
reality and I think the phenomenologist
I think
Punkie and the others were also trying
to put their finger on this way in their
critique of what they call
intellectualism not what you mean by
intellectualism but it's the same thing
that what James also use the same term
and again not the way you're using it
right now but this idea that we can get
caught up in right the these
abstractions and take them to have a
kind of reality that we and we have we
forget we forget the processes by which
they emerge and we are then cut off from
the life world we're cut off from what
what you know what I talked about yet
being actually coupled to our body to
each other into the world and that's
what James was really really really
critical of and so the idea of private
ism was that and you know and I had lots
of criticisms of James and how he uses
this term I think he was ultimately
trying to talk about relevance but
that's another that's another thing
right that we should be paying attention
to the use that these concepts perform
for us and and Andres and we situate
them back within how we how they are
conditioned by and conditioning of our
in active interaction with each other in
the world sorry you asked our definition
I don't think a definition is quite what
I gave you but that's a good
characterization I think oh yeah yeah
and that's that's a great complex
definition let me try to give a simple
one for for myself and for listeners
because what I part of what I put in my
the article on racism and when you
search the term this comes up is the
idea of vicious abstraction as
misquotation
and and I really like that because
you're cutting off the context yeah
right and there's the last the last of
contextualization is games as main part
okay I think that's what you're saying
there so yeah when you misquote you
literally don't pay attention to the
context yeah yeah and there's different
types of misquotation I I go and I go
into the details a little bit but just
you know I think the idea of
misquotation it's so ubiquitous
you can once you frame it in those terms
you can see it everywhere right in
discourse and in the framing of concepts
and it's just it's just that it's you're
just you just you're just cutting off
part of the context that complete
changes the meaning of the thing that
you're trying to say or convey and this
is just you know I love the word vicious
because it implies a lot of a lot of
violence and kind of malice even nice
but also price yeah vice yeah yeah
exactly it's oh so virtuous abstraction
would be would be the opposite and and
that is not a well-defined developed
term in in in what I've if you'll allow
me because you did make the connection
between abstraction and abduction and
I'm glad Plato's notion of an agog a and
reciprocal opening as a way of trying to
get what a virtuous abstraction looks
like and that's what I get from book
Latinas because we're trying to stick
that framework and then said yes but
what's my positive existential on
ultimately spiritual relationship to
that framework and how can I use that
try to abstract myself up to realize
myself more and more and so that's
that's part of what I'm trying to do
with that notion they are trying to
bring that notion back is trying to get
up but what's the virtuous version of
making use of this human capacity for
self transcendence because that's that's
what that's what the abstraction is
actually rooted in but it's I mean the
device I would argue comes from
perverting that primary ability for a
human self transcendence and and and
what that means there shouldn't virtues
of sub transcendence and instead of
maybe giving a definition maybe trying
to articulate the virtues of self
transcendence would be the way of trying
to articulate what and virtuous
obstruction is and that's a proposal I
give for you yeah and I I want to be
careful here you know because what what
comes to mind is the you know the the
schism or the contrast between
psychology and sociology and I've
written about this a bit in different
places it's a constant theme I'm a
sociological
I in a world of mostly psychological
psychologists Thai people and so with
with virtue and with the wisdom
tradition right and stoicism it's
awesome it's often framed in terms of
the individual and you know and how
could it not be right so but but I mean
sorry I want to I want to get there
because I mean I I have been developing
and I think this is not a maverick in
this sense this is a key feature for you
carbon science the centrality of
distributed cognition the breaking out
of the monolithic mind breaking out of
monological thought into biological I
mean this has been something that I
think is properly being emphasized now
and developed by a lot of people so I
think if you I would make an argument
that there is a and I'm not trying to
push I'm not trying to dismiss here but
I think I would say that there is a
community of people within the
psychological camp broadly construed or
engaging in a very powerful form of self
correction around exactly this issue
that's great yeah um yeah and not not
not to not to single you out in any way
but but I wish that was you know I I
still have higher hopes I want to see
more and you know a psychologist that
comes to mind right to defer it from
from us completely as Steven Pinker
right I made this point to to to daniel
Gertz yesterday is like you know the
critique and in Jacobin came out of
steven pinker and you know the the
headline is is a bit rude it's like it's
like yeah it's proven Steven Pinker's
full of shit but the article is great
right and and this is the point like
Steven Pinker can't take critique right
he gets into feuds with people like uh
what's his name
Phil hmm Phil Torres and many of many
other people right but so there's no
there's no auto critique there's no
reflexivity and and you know Pinker
really leans in to the kind of brand of
the optimist right it's it's it's like
you know
you know so to make the move to
sociology you know is there's heat much
bigger implications for that and and
this is why I titled my article like
inside View mapping meta modernism for
collective intelligence right there
wasn't a lot of space to unpack that but
it's kind of a jab at what's happening
with this term collective intelligence
and intelligence is the operative word
there because it's a lot of people
instrumentalizing this you know whether
it's in like you know Silicon Valley
communities or whatever that reinforces
that distinction from like the masses of
people right and and what we want to
foster is intellect distributed
intellect and so literacy I mean there's
not even a basic literacy
well maybe I'm talking about something
similar to this then because I talk a
lot about because I'm you know I have an
attitude towards intelligence I think
and tell that which makes this adaptive
also makes us prone to self-deception
and so I think I say the project should
be about trying to maybe maybe you won't
like this but I think about the way I
see individual wisdom as using
intelligence to acquire a psycho
technology of sub correction that
affords rationality the way we've talked
about it I've talked about that we
should be trying to cultivate collective
rationality largest collective
intelligence and I thought that to me is
it is a central project right now yeah
yeah and I think with with self
correction like like we can we could
keep you know anything with the self
again self-deception is is very is very
subtle like because you know we all know
geniuses that have some pathologies and
and and then it's kind of a paradox and
how do you challenge that person it's
like they're threatened by by your
critique and then there's implications
for them and how much they've invested
in that line of thought so people
underestimate the implications of self
critique you know of metanoia
which is like a deeper spiritual and
intellectual conversion I think yeah I
think there's a spiritual aspect to this
Brent yeah well that that okay but that
first of all I would like to
invite you to come back in August and we
do another one of these four voices with
verve a key and if if if you're if
you're in agreement with it
I'd like it to zero in on that last very
provocative point because I don't want
to just leave that sort of dangling the
spirituality which is something I'm very
interested and I don't like that term as
you know but it's there's no other term
right now the spirituality of all this
because you sort of brought it out and
you've alluded to it in a couple places
and you invoke the term drawn from the
heart of you know Neoplatonic
Christianity metanoia so I'd like to
bring out because this is also an area
where I think what we would talk about
with intersect with laymen right the
spirituality of meta modernism and what
you and your project if you yeah that's
great okay that's perfect that that's
that's perfect because other people have
been asking me about this and actually
I'm gonna talk to layman about it soon
and just your full disclosure my eat my
contribution to Jonathan Rosen's a meta
modern book is about Metanoia but but
it's up in the air whether I'm gonna
still contribute that because I'm
actually gonna try to publish on
Metanoia on my blog as soon as possible
because I just want to get get this
content out there and and then we can
talk about it so I'm really glad you
picked up on that at the end and I look
forward to that discussion oh well great
so maybe maybe what you could do and I
will I will respect your complete
intellectual property over it but maybe
you can send me the most recent draft oh
sure sure sure yeah and then I could
meet it and that would give me a little
bit of background that we could go into
it because I mean this is a concept
that's very important to me - sure Brent
this has been really wonderful it's I
hope you feel that you were given like a
welcoming space because absolute that
was my genuine intent I'm here and I
really enjoyed this I mean there's
there's points of difference but I
thought there was a genuine good faith
dialogue which is and I've said this
before and and you've earned my trust
miss Preston should be earned if I get a
sense that people even if they differ
from the in certain ways are willing to
enter into good-faith dialogue that I
want to talk to them especially if
they're bringing in the kind of insight
and the occu men that you are bringing
to
so thank you very much right on yeah in
inside porn as Peter Lindbergh would
probably get really turned on about so
yeah I really appreciate the the
welcoming context here and it's enabled
me to have a good dialogue with you so
thank you okay well thank you very much
and I guess I'll stop recording at my
end here and and that should